Animation Number 1
Before I start the story, here's a little preface. Though it's more like a warning.
（忍(しのぶ)）
話に入る前に
少しだけ前置きというか
諸注意を述べておくことにするが
お前様　わしは これから
You should know that I'm going to talk about when I created my first minion.
１人目の眷属(けんぞく)を作ったときの話を
することになるのじゃけれど
Don't get jealous.
嫉妬は せんようにな
Now, where should I begin?
さて 何から話したものかのう
Right. First, the circumstances...
そうじゃな まずは経緯かの
The circumstances with which I visited this country, Japan.
わしが この国… 日本を訪れた経緯
I was in top form and at my prime then. It was the best of times, it was the worst of times.
当時 わしは全盛期にして最盛期
最盛期にして再生期
Before I came here, I was in Antarctica. I wanted to see auroras and such.
来日の以前 わしは南極におった
オーロラとか見たくての
しかし
結果から言えば失敗じゃった
But the trip was a failure.
No, it's not that I'm not good with the cold. The problem was there were no people in Antarctica.
いや 別に寒いのが苦手
というわけじゃあない
問題はの 南極には
人がおらんということじゃよ
Stories of aberrations don't stand without talk of seeing or experiencing them.
目撃証言 体験談なくして
怪異譚(かいいたん)は成立しないのじゃ
Penguins and polar bears aren't going to talk about me,
ペンギンやシロクマ相手に
いくら わしの不死身性 化け物性を
発揮したところで
even if they witness my immortality and my monstrous nature.
連中が それを話題にしてくれる
わけではないからのう
I wasn't going to freeze to death, but somehow, I felt my existence beginning to weaken.
凍え死ぬことはないにせよ
何じゃろう… 己の存在力が
弱まっていくのを感じたからな
"This is bad!" "It's a huge crisis!" is what I thought.
おお これはマズいと
大ピンチじゃと わしは思った
I hurriedly escaped from Antarctica with a huge joystick-pushing jump.
慌てて わしは南極を脱出した
レバー入れ大ジャンプで脱出した
ん？　付喪神(つくもがみ)娘のジャンプ？
That tsukumo-gami girl's jump? Hmph, something like that pales in comparison.
フンッ そんなもんとは
比べ物にはならんよ
Frankly, the recoil from my jump almost destroyed the continent of Antarctica.
わしのジャンプは はっきり言って
南極の大地を反動で
ぶっ壊さんばかりじゃったぞ
I jumped randomly, so I thought I'd fall into the ocean,
でたらめに飛んだから
どうせ海に落ちると思っておったし
and I was thinking I'd take a swim to freshen up.
そのまま ひと泳ぎして
さっぱりしようと思っとったんじゃ
すると そこに あに図らんや
But there, to my surprise, was this country.
この国があったというわけじゃよ
I fell into a lake. How I obliterated that lake by doing so starts the story.
湖に落ちた
その際 その湖を
消滅させてしまったところから
物語は始まる
ろくでもない 鬼の物語が…
The story of a good-for-nothing demon.
Shinobu Time         Part Two
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Animation Number 3
So, do you know what landing in a lake after a huge leap from Antarctica does?
（忍）
で お前様
南極から大ジャンプしたわしが
湖に着水すると どうなると思う？
そう “水が跳ね上がる”じゃ
Right. "The water splashes up." Almost all the water in the lake did. And what does that splashed-up water do?
湖の水 ほとんど全てがの
After momentarily flying high in the air, it follows gravity and falls to the ground as "rain."
そして 跳ね返った水が
どうなるかといえば
一旦は天高く舞うにしろ
ただ重力に従って
地面へ落ちるだけじゃ
雨としてな
Back then, the drought around the lake was so bad that the ground was cracking.
当時
その湖の周辺の日照り 干ばつは
地面を割るような強烈さじゃった
I just happened to "make it rain" there.
わしは そこに
たまたま雨を降らせた
As a result, I saved many lives...
結果としてじゃが
わしは多くの命を… どころか
湖周辺の集落を
Or rather, I saved all the communities in the vast region around the lake.
まとめて 広範囲にわたって
救ってしまったわけじゃな
Further, I had terrible timing, since someone witnessed the act that saved them.
で タイミングの悪いことに
その たまたまの部分を
目撃されてしまっての
Of all things, someone saw the moment that created that "miracle."
よりにもよって
奇跡を起こした その瞬間をな
By the way, do you know what humans call someone who creates a "miracle"?
ところで お前様
奇跡を起こした者が
人間どもから何と呼ばれるか
知っておるか？
Right. Those who create miracles are called "gods."
そう 奇跡を起こした者は
神と呼ばれるのじゃよ
To be precise, those who create miracles, whether aberration or human, are turned into "gods."
正確には 奇跡を起こした者は
怪異であろうと人であろうと
神にされてしまうのじゃ
Animation Number 5
Apparently that lake was the object of some sort of worship.
（ラジオ:忍）
どうも その湖
何らかの信仰の対象に
なっておったようでな
The area's residents called it "God's Lake," revered it, and prayed to it. In other words, they prayed for rain.
周辺の住民は
その湖を神の湖として崇(あが)め
そして 祈っておった
つまり 雨乞いをしておった
Well, to them, it looked like I burst into existence from within the lake.
まあ 連中にしてみれば
わしが湖の中から
爆誕(ばくたん)したように見えたじゃろう
As if the lake's waters incarnated and appeared as me.
湖の水が具現化して
わしが登場したようにな
（阿良々木(あららぎ)）当時の日本人にとって
To Japanese people then, if a tall, golden-eyed blonde like you showed up,
いきなり金髪金眼(きんがん) 長身の
お前が現れたら
それなりに
神々しくは見えるだろうな
she'd look like a deity in some way.
They made Shinobu into a god
Animation Number 6
However
However...
Animation Number 6
But I don't think that would last long.
けど それ
絶対 長続きしないよな
Why's that?
（ラジオ:忍）
ん？　なぜじゃ
Well, judging from your personality.
いや お前の性格からしてよ
You're not the type that's all right with merely being revered.
ただ崇め奉られるのを
よしとするってタイプ
じゃねえだろ お前は
Fickle
Animation Number 9
In Personality
A vampire fixated on being a demon.
Animation Number 9
Just like you said, such a life as a god didn't last for long.
（ラジオ:忍）
お前様の言うとおり
そんな神様生活は
長続きせんかったがの
I think it was about a year.
およそ１年というところか
わしの性格がどうとかは ともかく
Besides my personality, I probably...
...wasn't fit to be a god.
わしが神様向きでないのは
確かじゃったろうな
Hachikuji Mayoi, at our side, still hasn't regained consciousness.
（阿良々木）
八九寺真宵(はちくじまよい)は
僕たちの脇で
まだ意識を取り戻さない
Animation Number 14
Well, after being set up by the people as a god,
（忍）
まあ アホな連中が わしを
“神様”と祭り上げたところに
staying there meant a break for me, so I was in good spirits.
調子よく乗っかって居ついたのは
休憩という意味合いもあった
何せ神様扱いじゃ
I mean, treated as a god?
寝床にも食い物にも
困らんかったしな
It was easy to find a place to sleep and food to eat.
It felt like a small vacation.
ちょっとしたバカンス
という感じじゃった
My bed, to be precise, was created.
わしの寝床は 正確に言うと作った
なくなってしまった湖の湖底にな
At the bottom of the lake that was now gone.
I built what you'd call a shrine. A very gorgeous building.
いわゆる社(やしろ)を建てた
とてもゴージャスな建物をな
ん？　そんな困窮した村に
Hmm? What a terrible god I am for forcing a village under such duress to build a shrine?
社を建てさせることを
要求するなんぞ
なんてひどい神様だ… じゃと？
自分で建てた
I built it myself. Did you forget my ability to create physical materials?
忘れたのか？
わしの物質具現化能力
それも全盛期のわしじゃ
This was me in my prime.
建物や
それに付随するガジェットなんぞ
I could easily make buildings and the gadgets that came along with them.
すぐに作れたわい
ちゅうか お前様
Or rather, you sitting there in just your underwear is becoming an eyesore.
いいかげん そのパンツ１枚の姿も
見苦しいの
服を作ってやるから それを着ろ
I'll make you some clothes, so wear them.
Hmm, looking pretty good. It suits you, it suits you.
ふむ いい感じじゃ
似合う似合う
I was doing proper work as a "god" too.
ちゃんと
神様としての仕事もしておった
雨というのは 一度降らせればいい
というわけでもなかったからの
It wasn't like rain was something I only had to make fall once.
At random intervals, I made it rain for them.
適当に間(ま)を置いて
雨を降らせてやった
その辺から雨雲を集めての
I gathered rain clouds from around the region.
まあ 快適といえば快適じゃった
If you call it comfortable, it was comfortable.
暇潰しというか… 暇を堪能した
A way to kill time, or rather, to be satisfied with free time.
I had thought that my power of existence would revive as long as they kept "witnessing" me.
そこで
連中に目撃され続けておれば
そのうち存在力も回復するとばかり
思っておったのじゃが
But unfortunately, life isn't quite that easy.
残念ながら
そうは問屋が卸さんかった
Because they weren't "witnessing" me as an aberration, as a "vampire,"
なんとなれば 連中は わしを
吸血鬼という怪異として
目撃しておったわけでは
ないのじゃから
there was no way my powers would revive. It took me a while to realize that.
回復するわけもない
それに気付くのに結構かかった
If I couldn't be "witnessed" as a vampire, that was fine as well.
吸血鬼として目撃されないのならば
それはそれで よかったのじゃ
That in and of itself wasn't an imminent problem.
別に それは
差し迫った問題ではなかった
問題は
神として目撃され続けたことじゃ
The problem was that I was continuing to be "witnessed" as a "god."
If you play with the devil, you become the devil.
悪魔と遊べば 悪魔になる
ならば 神と呼ばれれば 神になる
And in that case, if someone calls you a god, you become a god.
I really was careless for not realizing that... No, worse yet, for not even knowing that at all.
それに気付かなかったわしは…
いや 知りさえもしなかったわしは
本当に うかつじゃった
今から思えば
神扱いなど受け入れず
Now that I think about it, what I should've done...
その地に吸血鬼伝説がないことを
知った時点で
...was to reject the treatment as a god and depart once I realized the region had no vampire legends.
立ち去るべきじゃったのじゃろう
You can simply say that I got what was coming to me because I was pretending to be a god.
神様のふりなんぞを
続けておったから
罰(ばち)が当たったのじゃと
単純に言ってしまうことも
できるじゃろうがの
At least, that's what he said.
少なくとも
あやつは そう言っておった
He... That's right. My first minion.
あやつ…
そう １人目の眷属じゃ
つまりは
妖刀(ようとう)“心渡(こころわたり)”の持ち主じゃな
In other words, the owner of the demon sword "Heartspan."
That man had been fighting...
あの男は戦っとった
He fought even in those peaceful days. The days that in a way were more peaceful than the present.
あんな平和な
ある意味 今よりも平和じゃった
あの時代においても
戦っとった
Against what, you ask?
何と？
If you're not fighting humans, there are only certain things you can fight against.
人と戦わんというのならば
戦う相手は限られていよう
そう… 怪異とじゃよ
Right! He fought aberrations.
Animation Number 16
Fight aberrations...
（阿良々木）怪異と戦う？
え… それって
つまり 専門家ってことか？
Huh? So in other words, he's one of those specialists?
No.
Animation Number 18
あ…
ヴァンパイア･ハンター
No.
Animation Number 18
"Fighting" feels wrong.
Rather—
Animation Number 18
Koyomi / Conclusion
Vampire hunter.
Animation Number 18
Koyomi / Conclusion
Well, I guess that would be right.
まあ そうなのじゃろうな
The descendant of a long-standing clan that made a living by defeating monsters...
妖怪退治を生業(なりわい)とする
由緒正しき 一族の末裔(まつえい)
とか言っておったような
言っておらんかったような…
...I think was what he said. Or maybe he didn't...
Around now would be a good time to disclose the name of this first minion, wouldn't it?
（阿良々木）そろそろ ここらで
その１人目の眷属ってヤツの名前を
明かしてくれないか
Otherwise, I can't really imagine his face.
でないと
そいつの顔が見えてこないよ
I don't know.
知らん
I only vaguely remember proper names of the human world.
わしは人間界の固有名詞は
曖昧にしか記憶できんし
それに 誰の名前も呼びもしとらん
And I never call anyone by their name.
Isn't that too cold-hearted?
Animation Number 21
Iron-blooded
Hot-blooded
Animation Number 21
Where did that go?
I had always called him "Aberration Killer."
わしは そやつのことを ずっと
“怪異殺し”と呼んでおったしの
Just like I am called now.
わしが今 そう呼ばれておるように
He carried a sword, so it was easy to differentiate him from the others.
刀を持っておったから
ほかの人間とは
区別はつきやすかったし
専門家特有の空気もあったしの
He also had that aura only specialists have.
Well then, out of convenience, we'll call him the "original Aberration Killer."
じゃあ 便宜的に そいつのことは
“初代怪異殺し”とでも
呼んでおくか
The first aberration killer
Animation Number 22
The first servant
A specialist in defeating monsters...
妖怪退治の専門家ってことは
当然 お前を退治しに来た
ってことで いいんだよな？
So, of course, I assume he came to defeat you?
どこかから
お前のうわさを聞きつけて
After hearing rumors of you from somewhere, he showed up to defeat you.
お前をやっつけに現れたという…
No. Not like that, no...
（忍）否 違う違う
I did end up in a battle once, but he didn't arrive in order to defeat me.
一度 バトルにはなったが
しかし あやつは
わしを退治するために
やって来たわけではない
I mean, think about it.
じゃって 考えてもみよ
In every rumor that he heard from somewhere, I was revered as a god.
聞きつけたという
そのうわさの中において
わしは神として
崇められておったのじゃから
I was not a target to be defeated.
退治すべき対象では
なかったのじゃよ
Animation Number 25
He had merely come by to check things out.
そやつは とりあえず
様子を見に来たわけじゃ
“湖が１つ消滅し
そこから 神が顕現した”
A lake had disappeared and manifested itself as a god.
なんちゅう話を聞けば
A "man of a long-standing clan" couldn't dismiss rumors of something like that.
それは由緒正しき身としては
捨ててはおけんよな
Come to think, he arrived in one of those palanquins.
そやつは そういえば
駕籠(かご)に乗って現れたがの
He had rows of henchmen behind him. It was almost like a stately procession.
お供を ぞろぞろ引き連れてな
さながら 大名行列のような
ありさまじゃったぞ
I was drawn to the two katana, one large and one small, wielded by the man who stepped out.
駕籠から降りた その男が
持っていた大小２本の刀
それに わしは引き付けられた
The long katana was the demon sword "Heartspan". You've used a replica of it.
長いほうが妖刀“心渡”
お前様もレプリカを
使ったことのある あれじゃ
The other demon sword, the shorter katana, was named "Dreamspan".
２本目の妖刀 小太刀の名は
“夢渡(ゆめわたり)”じゃった
Animation Number 27
What kind of blade was the shorter katana?
（阿良々木）
小太刀ってのは
どういうものなんだ？
If "Heartspan" was a blade to kill aberrations, was the shorter one a blade to kill humans?
“心渡”が怪異を殺す刀なら
小太刀のほうは
人間を殺す刀なのか？
No, that would make it a normal katana.
いや…
それじゃあ ただの刀になるか
It was the "Aberration Reviver."
“怪異生かし”じゃよ
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
The small katana "Dreamspan" takes aberrations and brings them back to life.
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
小太刀〝夢渡〞は
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Heart Span
Longsword
Aberration Slayer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Dream Span
Aberration Restorer
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
Shortsword
Demon Sword
Dream Span
Heart Span
Longsword
The two are intrinsically linked
Animation Number 29
怪異を
生き返らせる刀じゃ
元より命のない怪異を
生き返らせるというのも
It's strange to say you're bringing a lifeless aberration back to life, but...
変な言い方に
なってしまうが
In other words, it's a katana that restores aberrations.
要は怪異を復活させる
ための刀じゃな
（阿良々木）ふうん
I see.
After that, they came to check up on me every so often. They'd chat with me a while, then go home.
以来 定期的に連中は
見回りにやって来て
わしと話をして帰っていく
Such visits repeated.
その繰り返しじゃった
I also helped them defeat monsters several times too.
何度か 連中の妖怪退治を
手伝ってやったこともあったか
背中を任せたのは そのときじゃの
That was when they had my back.
Hey, Shinobu...
なあ 忍
Why didn't you just turn into their god for good?
お前 だったら そのまま
神様になっちゃえば
よかったんじゃねえのか？
It sounds like you were well-suited. Like you were a perfect match for them.
話を聞いてたら 割と適役というか
スゲえ向いているふうじゃねえか
民を虐(しいた)げたりしてないし
You weren't oppressing your people or anything.
まあ 問題があるとすれば
If there were any issue, would it have been your impulse to suck blood?
お前にある吸血衝動
ってことになるのかな
Shinobu Voice / Speech
Animation Number 31
You idiot.
（忍）アホが
Shinobu Voice / Speech
Animation Number 31
The impulse to suck blood is problematic enough!
その吸血衝動という
問題があるだけで
十分じゃろうが
How obstinate.
Animation Number 32
Or rather, that wasn't the only problem.
というかの
問題は それだけではなかった
Animation Number 34
The aberration known as me... The problem was my existence as a vampire.
わしという怪異…
わしという吸血鬼の存在そのものが
問題じゃったわけじゃ
The existence of Kiss-shot Acerola-Orion Heart-under-blade as an aberration gathers aberrations.
わしという怪異は…
キスショット･アセロラオリオン･
ハートアンダーブレード—
という存在は 怪異を集める
However, what gathers aren't exactly aberrations, but negative energy that has yet to become aberrations.
それに 寄ってくるのは
怪異というより
怪異以前の
負のエネルギーじゃからのう
そういう よくないものじゃ
It's "bad stuff" of that sort.
And right. I was being careless.
そう… わしは うっかりしておった
I shouldn't stay in one location for an extended period of time.
わしは１か所に
長期間とどまってはいかんのじゃよ
I completely destroy the balanced ecosystem of aberrations.
怪異の生態系のバランスを
ごっそり崩してしまうゆえにな
And, what made me careless back then...
で このとき
うっかりしておったのは
それ以前に 南極という
...was how I had previously been in Antarctica, where no humans or aberrations existed.
人間も怪異も存在せん土地に
おったせいじゃ
I didn't realize at all that absolutely no "bad stuff" was gathered there.
よくないものが
全く そこに集まっていないことに
わしは全然 気付かなかった
The people of the region were the first to notice the problem.
事件に気付いたのは
近隣住民じゃった
It went like this.
こんな話じゃった…
人が消えるという
They heard stories about people disappearing.
Animation Number 35
They say — people don't come home after heading out.
出かけたまま帰ってこないという
Vanishing.
Animation Number 35
I talked it out with the original Aberration Killer as well, and we investigated.
初代怪異殺しとも
話し合ってみたが
そして 共に捜査をしてみたが
結論としては 証拠が出ないだけで
We couldn't find any evidence, so we concluded that it was probably a crime committed by a human.
これは人間の犯罪なんじゃないか
ということになった
This was not a job for us,
これは わしらの仕事ではない
It was no job for a god and a hunter of the supernatural,
Animation Number 35
it was a job for the police.
警察の仕事じゃとな
we decided.
Animation Number 35
In summary, I didn't do anything.
まとめると わしは何もせんかった
And still, they disappeared. The people of the region continued to go missing.
そんな中でも消えていった…
近隣の住民が行方不明になり続けた
And that continued until there were none.
誰もいなくなるまで それが続いた
Animation Number 36
What do you mean "until there were none"?
（阿良々木）
で 誰もいなくなったっていうのは
どういうことなんだ？
To me, you made it sound like every person in the area had disappeared.
お前の言い方 話しぶりじゃあ
周辺の住民が誰もいなくなった
というふうにしか
聞こえなかったんだよ 僕は
（忍）それで合っとる
That's correct. The entire settlement became deserted.
集落丸ごと
無人になってしまったのじゃから
The scale was too massive—
Animation Number 37
By far.
Just how many had disappeared?
Animation Number 37
After that, I looked in every village in the area.
それから わしは
近くの村を全部 回った
（阿良々木）ほう
I see.
And, as a result of my search, I found out...
（忍）
で その探索活動の結果
分かったことは
...that there was nobody left in any of the settlements in the area.
その辺りの集落には
もう誰も残っておらん
ということじゃった
As if someone drew boundaries. Every village past a certain point was safe.
境界線を引いたように
ある一定の地域から先の村は
無事じゃったようじゃがの
Border
Animation Number 137
Boundaries.
（阿良々木）
境界線…
Border
Animation Number 137
Partition
Those boundaries... In other words, "whether or not they worshiped you" had become a boundary?
その境界線ってのは つまり
お前を信仰していたかどうか
ってのが境界線になっていたのか？
Right. If you want to be more precise, it was "whether or not they knew me."
（忍）
そうじゃのう
より正確を期して言うならば
わしを知っておったかどうかじゃな
Worship had no connection.
信仰は関係ない
Empty villages.
Animation Number 40
Uninhabited settlements.
She visited them.
Animation Number 40
And well, I finally came to the realization...
そして まあ
ようやく わしは気付くわけじゃ
That negative energy had not piled up in the area at all,
わしが ここに随分と長く
滞在しておるにもかかわらず
even though I had resided there for quite some time.
負のエネルギーが
全くたまっておらんということに
So I thought, if there were any reason for that, it was...
原因があるとするなら
わしが ここに長居し過ぎたから
...those energies caused something to happen because I stayed there too long.
そのエネルギーが どこかで何かを
起こしたのじゃと思ったが
After looking around the area, I could find no evidence of it.
辺りを見回してみれば
特に そんなことはなかった
But it was still weird.
そんなことはなかったのが
おかしい
Strange. Something was abnormal. It was an abnormal situation.
異常じゃった
異常事態じゃった
Honestly, the fact that nothing had built up...
正直 わしにとっては
近隣住民が こぞって
いなくなってしまったことよりも
...was more mysterious than how all the inhabitants in the area had disappeared, and it grossed me out.
同じように近隣に
何も集まっていないことのほうが
不思議で 気持ち悪かった
It grossed me out, so I went home and napped.
気持ち悪かったから
家に帰って寝た
Come on!
（阿良々木）おい
（忍）え？
What? It's best to sleep things off when you're not feeling well, right?
（忍）気分が悪いときは
おとなしく寝るのが
いちばんなんじゃろう？
That's true, but still!
（阿良々木）そうだけども！
(Omitted)
Animation Number 45
So, to forget about it all, I tried to go back to sleep again.
（忍）
で すっきり忘れて
(Omitted)
Animation Number 45
わしは二度寝をしようと
したのじゃが
However, someone showed up to disturb me from my slumber.
しかし わしの眠りを
妨げる者が現れたのじゃ
Showed up...
（阿良々木）
現れたって…
...is that the enemy?
それが敵か？
Enemy
Animation Number 144
Darkness
Nope. The one who showed up...
（忍）うんにゃ 現れたのは
...was the original Aberration Killer.
初代怪異殺しじゃ
Animation Number 47
The new information was about the original Aberration Killer's henchmen.
新情報というのは
初代怪異殺しの
部下たちのことじゃ
They also disappeared. Gone. To somewhere unknown.
そやつらも いなくなった
消えた　どこかにの
And, before he knew it, the original Aberration Killer was left all alone.
で 気が付けば 初代怪異殺しは
１人になっておった
ということらしい
So, I, of course, heard his story out...
で わしとしては当然
そやつの話を聞いて
Unlike me, their sense of danger
Animation Number 48
was perfectly in order—
ならば
調査せねばならんのうと
...and with a grimace on my face, said, "Then we must investigate this."
Additionally,
Animation Number 48
their sense of fear.
しかつめらしく言った
I had already done my rounds of the villages once and knew of their current state.
既に わしは
一度 辺りの村々を回って
現状を把握してはおったが
もう一回
But I ended up going around the villages again with the original Aberration Killer.
初代怪異殺しと一緒に
村々を巡ることになった
Of course, there were no changes.
もちろん 変化などなかった
Those that were "spirited away" hadn't suddenly returned home.
神隠しに遭った連中が
不意に戻ってきておった
などということはなかった
Animation Number 49
Without warning, something evil happened.
（忍）
間の悪いことに いきなりじゃった
Suddenly—Without warning.
Animation Number 50
It appeared.
In the last village we visited, we found out the very last house we looked in was deserted.
最後に巡った その村で
最後に回った その家が
無人になっておったことが判明し
The original Aberration Killer was severely depressed.
初代怪異殺しが
好きなだけ へこんでおった
Right there, while he was delicately heartbroken...
デリケートに傷ついておった
その場に…
That was when it showed up.
そこに現れたのじゃよ
The thing that you call the "darkness"...
お前様が言うところの
“くらやみ”が
Completely disjointed, in the middle of the day...
何の脈略もなく
真っ昼間じゃというのにの
Finally it showed itself.
Animation Number 52
The real problem.
Animation Number 53
To be honest, I initially thought it was some strange weather pattern.
正直
最初は気象現象なのかと思った
I think it is most fitting to describe it as a black cluster...
黒い塊… と表現するのが
いちばん適しているような
気がするが
...but it didn't seem like it was solid enough to be called a cluster.
しかし 塊というほどに
固まっておるようにも思えんかった
It swallowed us. It swallowed both of us.
のまれた
２人とも のまれた
I realized, though a bit too late, that this was what had caused the spiriting away.
これが神隠しの正体か…
遅まきながら わしは そう気付いた
It had swallowed about three quarters of my entire body.
わしは 全身の４分の３くらい
のまれておった
But, well, if I had a quarter of me left, it was enough.
まあ しかし
４分の１も残っておれば
それで十分じゃった
At least to escape...
逃げるにはな
I, you know, flew down to Antarctica.
わしは あれじゃ
南極まで飛んだ
I didn't run away. I didn't run away.
Animation Number 54
I've never
run away from anything—
Animation Number 54
Even I have never have had my body shaved off in such a way before...
run away from anything—
Animation Number 54
さすがのわしも 自分の体を
あんなふうに削られたのは
初めてじゃったから
...so I just wanted to distance myself from it.
とにかく 距離を取りたかった
But apparently I didn't have to go that far.
しかし 結果から言えば
そこまでする必要はなかったの
That "darkness" never came chasing after me, no matter how long I waited.
その“くらやみ”は
追ってこんかったからじゃ
どれほど待とうとの
Well, under those circumstances, I left Japan.
まあ こういう経緯で
わしは日本を離れた
And I never went back.
そして そのまま戻らなかった
The next time I set foot in Japan was 6 months ago.
わしが次に日本に来るのは
半年前のことになる
And that is when I met you.
そして わしは
お前様に出会うことになる
Animation Number 55
Wait. What happened to the original Aberration Killer?
（阿良々木）ん？　ちょっと待て
初代怪異殺しは どうなったんだ？
Hmm? I already told you.
（忍）
ん？　じゃから言ったじゃろう
He got swallowed by the "darkness" with me.
わしと もろともに
“くらやみ”にのまれたよ
I was spared at three quarters,
わしは４分の３で済んだが
先にのまれた あやつは
４分の３どころでは済まんかったな
but he was swallowed first, so three quarters didn't cut it for him.
Almost his entire body was gone.
ほぼ全身 いかれたわい
That's strange, Shinobu.
（阿良々木）おかしいだろ 忍
If you're saying that the "darkness" swallowed him up, then the story ends there.
そこで“くらやみ”に そいつが
のまれてしまったっつうんなら
そこで
話が終わっちゃうじゃないか
No, no, you got it wrong. Listen closely.
（忍）
いやいや そうじゃなくっての
よく聞けよ
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I think I said that almost his entire body was swallowed up by the "darkness."
そやつが
“くらやみ”にのまれたのは
ほぼ全身と言ったはずじゃよ
わしは
You did. That's why I'm voicing my doubts.
（阿良々木）言ったよ
だから
疑問を呈しているんだろうが
If so...
（阿良々木）それじゃあ…
（忍）“ほぼ”
Almost.
In other words, there was a part of him left.
つまり 一部は残った
His right hand and wrist.
（忍）右手首が残った
（阿良々木）ん？
Hmm?
Wrist?
（阿良々木）
手首？
I told you he got swallowed up before I did.
（忍）
先に そやつのほうが
のまれたと言ったろう
And when he did, he grabbed my wrist as if he was seeking help.
そして のまれる際に
そやつは
まるで助けを求めるように
わしの手首を つかんだのじゃ
Grasped it firmly, like this.
こんなふうに ガチッと
（阿良々木）ああっ…
I had jumped down to Antarctica along with his hand and wrist.
わしは あやつの手首と一緒に
南極にまで飛んだのじゃった
Animation Number 68
In the end, I was left behind in Antarctica with his hand and wrist.
結局 わしは南極に１人
そやつの手首と共に
取り残されてしまった
ということじゃ
Left behind.
取り残された
I was all alone.
独りぼっちになった
It was the first time in a hundred years I had felt that way.
100年ぶりに そんなふうに思ったよ
I was seized by an incredible sense of isolation.
とんでもない孤独感に
とらわれてしまった
I'm sure it didn't help that it happened right after encountering
“くらやみ”という正体不明の
現象に遭遇した直後だったことも
an unidentifiable phenomenon like the "darkness".
もちろん 影響しておるのじゃろう
I didn't feel danger or uneasiness, but I did feel threatened.
危機感や不安感とは言わんまでも
脅威は感じた
That is why...
じゃから わしは
...I revived him.
よみがえらせた
I made my first minion.
１人目の眷属を作ったのじゃ
There's that misattribution of arousal...
つり橋効果っちゅうのがあるよな
Something like a rapid heartbeat from fear of heights...
つり橋の上の
恐怖心から来るドキドキと
恋愛感情のドキドキを
取り違えてしまうとか… のう
...being mistaken for a rapid heartbeat from being in love.
つまり つり橋の上
だったり何だったり
In summary, whether atop a tall bridge,
If you explain it like that,
Animation Number 69
it's rather easy to understand,
or in any situation where you feel your life is in danger,
命の危機を感じる状態に
追い込まれると
but that effect
Animation Number 69
is open to interpretation.
organisms tend to fall in love more in an effort to leave progeny.
生物は子孫を残そうと
恋に落ちやすくなるとか
Love and romance... Families and minions...
恋とか愛とか
家族とか眷属とか
It's nothing emotional like that.
そんなエモーショナルな
ものじゃあない
More impulsive and unable to be restrained. That's my reason.
衝動的な
This is where
Animation Number 69
褒めようのない
理由なのじゃよ
disappointment kicks in.
Animation Number 69
My heart was weakened.
心が弱っただけ
With a chomp, I bit into his right wrist,
ガブリと わしは
あやつの右手首にかみついて
and I sucked its blood.
血を吸った
Not as a meal, but to create a minion,
食事ではなく 眷属を作るために
I sucked its blood.
血を吸った
Because I didn't want to be alone, I stopped being a god and returned to being a vampire.
独りが嫌で
神様をやめ 吸血鬼に戻った
Animation Number 70
So, did you succeed?
（阿良々木）で 成功したのか？
I failed.
失敗した
F-Failed?
し… 失敗？
Just as I expected, the original Aberration Killer came back to life.
わしのもくろみどおり
初代怪異殺しは生き返った
しかし お前様ほど
However, I guess he wasn't as mentally strong as you are.
メンタルが強くなかった
ということなのかな
In hindsight, I guess I just wasn't considerate enough.
今から思えばじゃが
わしの気遣いが
足らんかったのじゃろう
If I recall, he jumped into sunlight of his own will, turned to ash, and was no more?
自分から太陽の下に飛び出して
灰になって消えたんだっけな…
確か
Right.
（忍）そう… 自殺
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Suicide...
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Unavoidable.
Animation Number 74
It was unavoidable.
His suicide.
Animation Number 74
A very, very common reason for vampires to die. Roughly 90 percent die that way.
吸血鬼の死因の
およそ９割を占める
ごくごく平凡な死亡理由… じゃ
Regenerating in the flames.
Animation Number 75
Regenerating in the flames
Until everything is burned to ash.
Animation Number 75
You didn't save him?
（阿良々木）
そのとき
助けてやらなかったのか？
Just like you did during spring break when I went into the sun.
春休みに
太陽の下に出てしまった僕を
そうしてくれたように
That would be impossible.
無理じゃったなあ
Back then, I didn't quite understand the meaning behind such actions by him.
当時のわしには
ヤツの その行動の意味が
よく分からんかったしな
Or rather, I had many conversations with him until he decided to commit suicide...
というか そやつが自殺を選ぶまで
さんざん会話を交わしたもんじゃが
...but by then, my relationship with him had completely broken down.
その時点で ほとんど
あやつと わしとの関係は
破綻しておったからのう
There was no way to stop him.
止めようがなかった
（阿良々木）破綻って？
Broken down?
Missing the mark
Animation Number 77
Just missing the mark
To make it easy to understand, he was angry.
分かりやすく言うと
怒っておったのじゃよ
初代怪異殺しは
The original Aberration Killer was angry that I had turned him into a vampire.
わしが あやつを
吸血鬼化させたことをな
Not a god, a demon.
Animation Number 78
He learned she was a vampire.
After reviving him from just one hand and wrist...
手首１つから生き返り
...and after he gained a new life as a vampire, the first thing he said to me was...
吸血鬼として
新たなる命を得た初代怪異殺しが
わしに対して最初に発したセリフは
"You monster! How dare you scheme against us!"
（忍）
“この化け物が”
“よくも私たちを謀(たばか)ったな”
He yelled at me.
じゃったな…
"So everything was your doing!"
全て貴様のせいだったのかと
どなられた
Though he wasn't merely yelling, but placing blame.
どなるというよりは
なじるという
ニュアンスじゃったかのう
That's when he began talking about "receiving divine punishment" and such too.
天罰が下った云々(うんぬん)のセリフも
そのときに言われた
In other words, he thought everything, including the "spiriting away," was your fault.
（阿良々木）要は そいつ
神隠しから何から
全て お前のせいにしたってことか
That even the "darkness" was something you had set up...
その“くらやみ”も
お前の仕掛けか何かだと…
Wrong scale.
Animation Number 82
So, what did you do?
で お前は どうしたんだ？
No matter the motive, you somehow managed to save him.
動機はどうあれ 曲がりなりにも
助けてやったってのに
Yet after hearing that, you must have been unsettled.
そんなことを言われたら
内心 穏やかではなかっただろう
No, not really. It wasn't that bad.
（忍）
いや 別に… それほどでもない
Well, I found it a chore to undo the misunderstanding, so I let him say whatever he wanted to.
まあ 誤解を解くのとかは
面倒くさかったから
好きに言わせておいたがの
今は混乱し 錯乱しておるが
I thought he was confused and deranged, but he would calm down in due time.
しかし
そのうち落ち着くじゃろうとな
There wasn't the tiniest,
Animation Number 84
smallest,
minutest,
Animation Number 84
wish to save him—
That can't be true.
Animation Number 84
If she were that kind of woman,
then I wouldn't be here now.
Animation Number 84
I wouldn't be alive as a half-vampire.
However, he never calmed down.
しかし 落ち着かんかった
Confused, deranged, and after many confrontations with me...
混乱し 錯乱し
さんざん わしと対立した末に
そのまま投身自殺した
...he tossed his body in an act of suicide.
Saying all sorts of begrudging words to me...
わしに
さんざん恨み言を言いながら
...words of regret and resentment...
後悔と怨嗟(えんさ)の言葉にまみれながら
...he threw himself into the sunlight in front of my eyes and died.
わしの目の前で
太陽に
その身を投げ出して
死んだ
I couldn't stop him, and I couldn't save him.
止められんかったし
助けられんかった
I had told him my real name while we were in Antarctica.
南極に着いてからは
本名を教えてやったというのに
But in the end, he called me "Kiss-shot" only once.
結局 ヤツが
わしをキスショットと呼んだのは
Right before he committed suicide.
投身する直前の１回だけじゃったな
Even then, he called her Kiss-shot.
（阿良々木）
それでも
“キスショット”と呼んだのか
Not Heart-under-blade. Not Acerola-orion.
ハートアンダーブレードでも
アセロラオリオンでもなく
Kiss-shot. Just like me.
“キスショット”と 僕のように
If so...
だったら…
And so he died.
そして ヤツは死んだ
Because of the body's immortality, it is more precise to say that he ceased to exist than that he died.
不死身の身の上であるがゆえに
死んだと言うよりは
滅びたと言ったほうが正確じゃが
とにかく死んだ
But in any case, he died.
形見として
He left behind a replica of the demon sword "Heartspan" that he created from his flesh and bones.
己の骨身でこしらえた
妖刀“心渡”のレプリカを残しての
I'm sure he created it with the intent of killing me.
どうせ わしを殺すつもりで
作ったのじゃろうが…
Until then, for whatever reason, I had not made any minions.
それまで わしは
なんとなく眷属を
作っておらんかっただけであって
別に頑(かたくな)な意志を持って 独り身を
貫いておったわけではなかったが
It wasn't that I was persevering in my solitude out of stubbornness...
...but after seeing the blue blaze disappear, how his corpse vanished...
青く燃え上がって消えた
ヤツの死体の消滅を見届けて
...I swore that I would never make a minion again.
わしは
もう二度と眷属は作るまいと
I would never drink human blood for any purpose other than for nutrition.
栄養摂取以外の目的で
人の血は吸うまいと
誓ったのじゃった
I swore to god.
神にな
At the least, I couldn't laugh about that.
（阿良々木）
少なくとも
笑うことはできなかった
うまいことを言うと
感心することも
Nor admire her for her wit.
Because in the end, in spite of everything,
だって 結局 最終的には
she couldn't hit it off with humans as a "god" or a "vampire."
彼女は 神としても吸血鬼としても
人間と うまくやることは
できなかったのだから
The demon's soliloquy.
鬼の１人語りは
The story of 400 years ago.
今は昔の 400年前の物語は
With this bad ending, the curtain falls.
こうして
バッドエンドで幕を閉じる
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Karen here!
（火憐）火憐(かれん)だぜ！
（月火）月火(つきひ)だよ！
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
Devil!
（火憐･月火）
２人合わせて
ファイヤーシスターズ
A way to become a god?
I think you misunderstood.
（火憐）
12人合わせたら
If we gather 12 members, I want to be the Fire Sister Princess!
ファイヤーシスター
プリンセスだぜ
（月火）
とりあえず
Let's start by inviting Ononoki-chan, okay?
斧乃木(おののき)ちゃんを
仲間に入れよう
Preview Quiz!
（火憐）予告編クイズ！
（月火）クイズ！
Quiz!
（火憐）
「オズの魔法使い」
読んでるか？
Did you read "The Wonderful Wizard of Oz"?
Awesome! Show us how it's done!
I read it, I perused it, I devoured all of it!
（月火）
読んでる 読んでる
読み尽くしてる！
（火憐）
一緒に旅をする仲間
A journey with a company of three: the lion, the scarecrow and the tin robot.
ライオンと かかしと
ブリキのロボットじゃん
Indeed, the Big Three eh?
（月火）
そうだね 御三家だね
The robot and scarecrow characters are overlapping though...
（火憐）
かかしとロボット
キャラかぶってね？
Excited
It's up to you now...
Eh! I'm the one to do it?!
（月火）
両方 人型だ
Both are human-shaped!
（火憐）
かかしはロボットに
ならないにしても
While the scarecrow will never become a robot, isn't the opposite entirely possible?
ロボットは かかしに
なるんじゃないか？
The scarecrow has no reason to exist, be it on the road, or in a field.
かかし 立場ねえよな
旅の道中でも 畑でも
Plus one longs for a heart, and the other a brain, how similar is that.
（月火）
欲しいものも
心と脳みそで
甘かぶりしてるしね
（火憐）
両者の確執が
予想されるぜ
Both share too many similarities.
The same can be said about Toto and the lion though.
（月火）
それを言いだしたら
トトとライオンも
甘かぶりしてるような…
Next Time
Shinobu Time Part 3
Next time! Onimonogatari Episode 3!
（火憐･月火）
次回「鬼物語 第３話
しのぶタイム 其ノ参(そのさん)」
Shinobu Time, Part 3.
Rather than becoming a god,
He turned into Hotoke-sama!
（火憐）
リーダーとして
I'd like Oz to act more as the leader she is.
しっかり仕切って
ほしいよな オズ
（月火）
オズは
ヒロインの名前じゃない
Oz isn't the heroine of the story, you know...